Finding Aid for Richard C. Frank papers, 1958-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard C. Frank papers 1958-2004
Frank, Richard C.
1 oversize folders
90 tubes
43 linear feet
2008082 Aa 2
The papers of Richard C. Frank, preservation architect and planner, contain paper files as well as architectural drawings and sketches from Frank’s Preservation / Urban Design / Incorporated firm and from his work after leaving the firm in 1984. Major projects include Crossroads Village in Genesee County, the Detroit People Mover, Orchestra Hall of Detroit, and the Smithsonian Institution Art and Industries Building.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Richard and Jan Frank (donor no. 8541 ) in 1997, with additional accessions in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard C. Frank, preservation architect and planner, directed over 700 projects in 28 states during the course of his 40-year career, including the restoration of Fort Michilimackinac, Orchestra Hall in Detroit, Historic Crossroads Village of Genesee County, the Smithsonian Institution's Art and Industries Building, and the Thomas Jefferson Building at the Library of Congress. He is credited as being the "Father of Preservation" in the state of Michigan and helped raise public awareness about the value of the historic architecture and preservation.
Richard Frank received his Bachelor of Architecture from the University of Michigan in 1953 and served as an adjunct professor at Michigan's College of Architecture and Urban Planning. He was elected to the American Institute of Architects College of Fellows in 1974 and received the A.I.A. Michigan Gold Medal in 1992. The Frank papers at the Bentley Historical Library cover Frank's work as owner of Preservation / Urban Design / Incorporated and his later work as an FAIA architect after leaving P/UD/I in 1984.
Richard Frank died January 28th, 2008, in Detroit, Michigan.
The Frank papers are organized into six series: Project Files, Orchestra Hall, Crossroads Village, Smithsonian Institution Arts and Industries Building, Other Files, and Visual Material. The records contain paper files as well as architectural drawings and sketches. In most instances, the container list reflects the original order of the files. If a project number was written on a file folder or tube, this number is also recorded in the container list. Additionally, the majority of the material has been kept in its original folder.
Subjects:
Frank, Richard C.; Arts and Industries Building (Washington, D.C.); Fair Lane (Dearborn, Mich.); Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Orchestra Hall (Detroit, Mich.); People Mover (Detroit, Mich.); Historic preservation--Michigan.; Crossroads Village (Mich.); Mackinac Island State Park (Mich.)
Contributors:
Preservation Urban Design Incorporated.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Project Files
  The Project Files series covers Frank's work as owner of Preservation / Urban Design / Incorporated (P/UD/I) from 1975 to 1984 and later as an FAIA architect. The projects have been arranged alphabetically, reflecting the original order of the material. The series contains paper records supplemented with architectural drawings. (The project files for Orchestra Hall, Crossroads Village and the Smithsonian Institution Arts and Industries Building are each listed in their own, separate series.) In some instances, only architectural drawings or only paper files remain. Occasionally it was necessary to sketch how a location looked during different time periods, for example, the Detroit People Mover architectural drawings. The majority of architectural drawings are blue line prints, though there are a few original pencil and ink on mylar drawings. The paper files also may contain historic background materials. Other ephemera include maps, photographs, photographic negatives, and slides. The series contains two subseries: Saline Office (8.25 feet, 48 tubes) and Detroit Office (16 feet, 27 tubes). The Saline Office subseries represents an earlier accession, with materials originating from Frank's office in Saline, Michigan. The Detroit Office subseries covers the project files housed in Frank's office in Detroit, Michigan. There are some projects, which overlap between the two subseries. For example, the Saline Office subseries contains the architectural drawings for Ann Arbor Westside Neighborhood project, while the Detroit Office subseries contains the project's corresponding written plan.
  Michigan project files include: Albion Downtown Study, Applewood Estate in Flint, Central City Historic Survey in Grand Rapids, the Detroit People Mover, The Ford Fair Lane Building (now owned by the University of Michigan at Dearborn), the residences of Ann Arbor's Inter-Cooperative Council (or I.C.C.), Kalamazoo Depot and Water Tower Restoration, Lenawee County Museum, Michigan Theater in Ann Arbor, Old City Hall of Ypsilanti, St. Mary's Church of Detroit, and a restoration of the Woodward East section of Detroit. There are also architectural drawings of many Mackinac Island State Park structures. The paper records of the Fort Wilkins restoration project contain a wealth of historical information.
  Items in this series from outside of Michigan include architectural drawings of the Thomas Jefferson Building at the Library of Congress and Colonial Williamsburg.
  Richard Frank's renovation of the Dart residence in Okemos and Turner-Dodge House of Lansing provide a look at the historic restoration of residential homes, while a sampling of commercial projects include Goodyears Interiors and Rider's Hobby Shop of Ann Arbor and the South Bank Restaurant of Manistee.
  - Saline Office
    - Albion Downtown Study, Eaton Street 1980
      (project no.1320)
      - Project Records (incl. photos) (Box 1)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 10)
        (project nos. 1228, 1320)
    - Anderson, William Residence, Okemos, Architectural Drawings (Tube 20)
      (project no. 5081)
    - Ann Arbor Civic Theatre 1978 (Box 1)
      (project no.1233)
    - Ann Arbor, East Ann St. Study 1975 Architectural Drawings (Tube 9)
      (project no. 116, 1150, 1201)
    - Ann Arbor Fire Hall (incl. photographs of sketches), 5 folders (Box 1)
      (project no. 1252)
    - Ann Arbor, Westside Neighborhood, Architectural Drawings (Tube 9)
      (project nos. 116, 1150, 1201)
    - Bidwell Block, Tecumseh 1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (project no. 1168)
    - Boston Edison House Rehab, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (project no.1297)
    - Calumet Design Study, Phase II 1978-1980 (Box 1)
      (project no. 1282)
    - Calumet Downtown Study 1978-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (project no. 1236)
    - Calumet Theatre (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Library, Adrian 1977-1979 (Box 1)
      (project no. 1188)
    - Central City Historic Survey, Grand Rapids 1981, 3 folders
      (project no. 1328)
      - General Files (Box 1)
      - Churches (Box 1)
      - Transportation / Industries (Box 1)
      - Schools / Firehouses (Box 1)
      - Landmarks (Box 1)
      - Maps (Box 1)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 56)
    - Colonial Williamsburg 1981-1984 Architectural Drawings (Tube 35)
      (project no. 81-170)
    - Dart Residence, Okemos (incl. photographs), 1987
      (project no. 1.85.1)
      - Project Records, 19 folders (Tube 35)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 30)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 58)
    - Detroit Stove (Box 2)
      (project no. 11320)
    - Detroit People Mover 1981-1982
      (project no. 1322)
      - Project Records, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Architectural Drawings (incl. historical sketches of Detroit) (Tube 18)
    - Durand Depot Appraisal, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (project no.1241)
    - Durand Depot 1975-1979
      (project no.1243)
      - Project Records (incl. photographs), 3 volumes; 18 folders (Box 2)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 3)
    - Eastern Michigan University, Sherzer Hall, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (project no.1230)
    - East Lansing, Chittenden Hall 1980 Architectural Drawings (Tube 1)
      (project no.1293)
    - East Lansing Urban Design Project, 1 items; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Engine House Number Six Public Museum, Grand Rapids 1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (project no. 1186/136)
    - Fair Lane, University of Michigan at Dearborn
      - General (Box 3)
      - Photograph (Box 3)
      - Restoration Study, 2 folders (Box 3)
        (project no.1113)
      - Ford Fair Lane (Box 3)
        (project no.1171)
      - Pool Renovations
        (project no.1154)
        - Project Records (Box 3)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 55)
        (project no. 1154, 1215, 1216, 1231, 1248, 1271, 1287, 1302)
      - Cost Analysis (Box 3)
        (project no.1202)
      - Restoration Cost Brochure (Box 3)
        (project no.1223)
    - Fayette State Park, Architectural Drawings (Tube 32)
    - Ferry Seed Barn, Rochester (Box 3)
      (project no.1343)
    - Flint, Water Street District Study, 3 folders (Box 3)
      (project no.1213)
    - Fort Wilkins 1976 (incl. photographs, historical files, and maps), 7 folders (Box 3)
      (project no1122.)
    - Goodyears Interior, Ann Arbor 1983
      (project no. 19833)
      - Project Records, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Project Records (incl. photographs), 6 folders (Box 4)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 14)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 15)
        (continued)
    - Grand Haven Historical Survey, 2 folders (Box 4)
      (project no.1341)
    - Grekin Residence, Ann Arbor 1979
      (project no.1303)
      - Project Records (Box 4)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 7)
        (project no.1266)
    - Gun Lake Property Development
      (project no.1248)
      - Project Records (incl. photocopies of photographs), 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 55)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council, Ann Arbor 1979
      (project no1207.)
      - Anderson House, 4 folders (Box 4)
        (project no. 1305)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 12)
        (project no. 1305, 1308 1345)
      - Architectural and Engineering Report, Cost Estimate, 2 folders (Tube 12)
      - Brandeis House 1982
        (project no. 1345)
        - Project Records (Tube 12)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 12)
          (project no. 1305, 1308, 1345)
      - Bruce House
        (project no. 1207-106)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 37)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        (project no. 1207-101)
      - Debbs House
        (project no. 1207-109)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 41)
      - Joint House
        (project no. 1207-110)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 41)
      - Lester House
        (project no. 1207-111)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 41)
      - Master File (Box 4)
      - Michigan House, 2 folders
        (project no. 1207-103)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 40)
      - Minnie's House
        (project no. 1207-107)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 39)
      - Nakamura House
        (project no. 1207-104)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 38)
      - Osterweil House
        (project no. 1207-114)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 37)
      - Owen House
        (project no. 1207-102)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 38)
      - Stevens House
        (project no. 1207-112)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 37)
      - Vail House
        (project no. 1207-108)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 39)
      - Xanadu House
        (project no. 1207-113)
        - Project Files (Box 4)
        - Architectural Drawings (Tube 37)
      - Contracts, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Contracts, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Ionia Downtown Revitalization Study 1978-1979
      (project no. 1228)
      - Project Records, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 10)
        (project no. 1228 1320)
    - Kalamazoo Depot Restoration 1976-1977
      (project no. 1157)
      - Project Records (incl. photograph of sketch), 2 folders (Tube 10)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 2)
        (project no. 1125, 1127)
    - Kalamazoo Water Tower Restoration 1976
      (project no. 1127)
      - Project Records (incl. photographs), 7 folders (Box 5)
      - Architectural Drawings (Box 5)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 6)
        (project no. 1129)
    - Ladies Library Association, Kalamazoo 1975-1976, 5 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1118)
    - Lenawee County Historical Museum, Adrian 1982
      (project no. 1251)
      - Project Records, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 5)
    - Mackinac Island State Park
      - Architectural Drawings
        - Airport Terminal (Tube 21)
          (project no. 6892)
        - Coast Guard Station (Tube 22)
          (project no. 6901-B)
        - Fort Mackinac Commanding Officers Headquarters (Tube 23)
          (project no. 6222-B)
        - Governor's Residence, Fire Protection Work (Tube 24)
          (project no. 6733)
        - Orientation Center (Tube 25)
          (project no1902-A)
        - Priest House (Tube 26)
          (project no. 6902-B)
        - Soldiers' Barracks and Public Toilets (Tube 27)
        - Wastewater Treatment Facility (Tube 28)
          (project no. 7035)
        - Wastewater Treatment Plant (Tube 29)
          (project no. 7037)
      - Project Records
        - McGulpin House (Box 6)
          (project no. 19476.00)
    - Manistee, Dunham House
      - Architectural Drawings, Demolition Plans (Tube 31)
      - Architectural Drawings, Original Tracings (Tube 36)
      - Architectural Drawings, 4th Avenue Façade (Tube 42)
    - Manistee Preservation and Development Plan 1980-1984 (incl. photographs), 5 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1309)
    - Manistee Riverwalk (incl. photographs), 6 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1348)
    - Manistee, South Bank Restaurant 1980
      (project no. 1302)
      - Project Files, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 55)
    - Marquette County Court House, Marquette (Box 6)
      (project no. 1139)
    - Mexican Patriotic Community Center, Detroit, 2 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1312)
    - Monroe Center Heritage Conservation Study 1980, 6 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1274)
    - Monroe Downtown Revitalization, 4 folders (Box 6)
      (project no. 1307, 7292)
    - Monroe, Lake Erie Gateway Study (Box 7)
      (project no.1287)
      - Project Files (Box 7)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 55)
        (project nos. 1154, 1215, 1216, 1231, 1248, 1271, 1287, 1302)
    - Niles, Fort St. Joseph (Box 7)
    - North Lansing Historic District, 5 folders (Box 7)
      (project no. 1182)
    - North Lansing Historic Commercial District 1977-1980, 4 folders (Box 7)
      (project no. 1211)
    - Old Atlas Township Hall, Goodrich 1979
      (project no.1225)
      - Project Files, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 11)
    - Old City Hall Adaptive Reuse, Ypsilanti 1978-1979
      (project no.1240)
      - Project Files, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 8)
        (project nos. 1196, 1240, 1255, 1319)
    - Owosso, Pabst Building 1978 Architectural Drawings (Tube 55)
    - Real Invest, Ann Arbor 1980
      (project no.1308)
      - Project Files, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 12)
        (project nos. 1305, 1308, 1345)
    - Riders Hobby Shop, Ann Arbor
      (project no.1201)
      - Project Files, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 9)
    - Saline, Attitude Towards Annexation, Boundary Plan 1975-1979 (Box 7)
      (project no.1176)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 4)
        (project nos. 1133, 1140, 1153, 1176, 1194)
    - St. Mary's Church, Detroit
      (project no.1327)
      - Project Files (incl. photographs), 7 folders (Box 7)
      - Project Files, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 16)
    - Schoolcraft House, Sault Ste. Marie 1972, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Ticknor-Campbell House, Cobblestone Farm Association 1976
      (project no. 1137)
      - Project Files, 1 volumes; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 43)
    - United States Library of Congress, Thomas Jefferson Building, Architectural Drawings (Tube 54)
    - University of Detroit Campus Development Plan, 3 folders (Box 8)
      (project no.1175)
    - University of Michigan
      - Detroit Observatory (Box 8)
        (project no.1119)
      - Library / Museum / Arch (Box 8)
      - Quadrangle Law Club (Box 8)
    - Washtenaw County, Parker Mill, Architectural Drawings (Tube 57)
    - Wayne State University, Freer House, Architectural Drawings (Tube 52)
    - Wayne State University, Freer House, Architectural Drawings (Tube 53)
    - Weinmann Block, Ann Arbor, 2 folders (Box 8)
      (project no.1354)
    - Woodward East 1976
      (project no.1264)
      - Project Files, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 13)
        (project no.1145)
      - Architectural Drawings, "Woodward East II" (Tube 17)
    - Women's Club House, Lansing, 3 folders (Box 8)
      (project no. 1117)
    - Ypsilanti Gilbert House 1977-1979
      (project no.1196)
      - Project Files, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Architectural Drawings (Tube 8)
        (project nos.1196 1240, 1255 1319)
    - Ypsilanti City Hall, 2 folders (Box 8)
      (project no.1229)
  - Detroit Office
    - 500 Block of Albert Avenue, East Lansing, Architectural Drawings (Tube 60)
    - AAI -- Moravian Hall, Clinton Township 1997 (Box 18)
    - Adrian Carnegie Library, A Feasibility Study for Adaptive Reuse 1977 (Box 18)
    - Albion Commercial Areas Improvement Plan 1980 (Box 18)
    - Arkon Historic Conservation, A Plan for Managing Resources 1978 (Box 18)
    - Ann Arbor Downtown Façade Study 1976 (Box 18)
    - Ann Arbor Trolley, A Feasibility Study 1978 (Box 18)
    - Anna Scripps Whitecomb Conservatory Renovations, Architectural Drawings, blue line prints (Tube 61)
    - Applewood Estate, Flint
      - Photographs, 1995 (Box 18)
      - Inventory and Assessment Study 1995 (Box 18)
      - An Inventory and Assessment of its Building Report 1995 (Box 18)
      - Construction Documents 1996 (Box 18)
      - First Floor Interior Renovations, Project Manual 2004 (Box 18)
      - Finishes Study 2004 (Box 18)
      - Project files 1996-2004, 11 folders (Box 18)
      - Project files 1996-2004, 23 folders (Box 19)
      - Architectural Drawings, blue line prints and ink on mylar drawings, includes copies of original drawings (Tube 62)
      - Architectural Drawings, blue line prints and ink on mylar drawings, includes copies of original drawings (Tube 63)
    - Arcadia Commons, Kalamazoo 1990 (Box 19)
    - Avian Disease and Oncology Laboratory, East Lansing 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Bagley Avenue, A Revitalization Plan, Detroit 1980 (Box 20)
    - Battle Creek Railway Station (Box 20)
    - Belding City Hall
      - Existing Condition Analysis and Preliminary Space Use Plan 1999 (Box 20)
      - Project Files 1998-1999, 5 folders (Box 20)
      - Architectural Drawings, original pencil and ink on mylar drawings (Tube 64)
    - Belding Waterworks, 1998-199 (Box 20)
    - Bicycle Factory Housing, Grand Rapids, Architectural Drawings (Tube 65)
    - The Bidwell Building, A Feasibility Study 1977 (Box 20)
    - Bishop and Shelton, Ann Arbor, Architectural Drawings, originals pencil on mylar drawings and blue line prints (Tube 66)
    - Calumet Downtown Historic District Plan 1979 (Box 20)
    - Cathedral of the Blessed Sacrament, Detroit
      - Project Files 1999-2000, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Architectural Drawings, blue line prints (Tube 67)
    - Central City, Grand Rapids
      - List of Inventoried Properties 1981 (Box 20)
      - Historic Survey, Grand Rapids undated (Box 20)
    - Chelsea Depot, Chelsea 1986 (Box 20)
    - Cherry Hill Neighborhood, Grand Rapids 1993 (Box 20)
    - Chittenden Hall, Michigan State University
      - Analysis Phase 1980 (Box 20)
      - Schematic Phase 1981 (Box 20)
      - Project Files 1980, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Consolidated Packaging Corporation Complex, Monroe
      - Analysis and Evaluation 1980 (Box 20)
    - Cranbrook Institute of Science, Bloomfield Hills 1998 (Box 20)
    - Crossroads Village Farm, Flint
      - Master Plan 1980 (Box 20)
    - Dart Residence, Okemos, Architectural Drawings, blue line prints (Tube 68)
    - Depot Town, Ypsilanti, A Preservation Plan 1976 (Box 20)
    - Detroit Stove 1973-1998, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Downtown East Lansing
      - Façade Study Report undated (Box 20)
      - Design Guidelines Manual 1995 (Box 21)
      - Summary Report 1995 (Box 21)
    - The Earle Hotel and Garage, Ann Arbor 1974 (Box 21)
    - Eloise Property, Wayne County
      - Master Site and Facility Plan 2001 (Box 21)
      - Project Files, 2000-2001, 7 folders (Box 21)
    - Emmanuel Lutheran Church, Ypsilanti 1992, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Eustace Hall, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Architectural Drawings, blue line prints (Tube 69)
    - Fair Lane, Henry Ford Estate, Dearborn
      - Feasibility Plan for the Preservation and Adaptive Reuse of Fair Lane 1975 (Box 21)
      - Historic Preservation Master Plan Proposal 2001 (Box 21)
      - Project Files 1998-2001, 4 folders (Box 21)
    - Farnum Building Tunnel, Michigan State Senate 1988 (Box 21)
    - Fayette Hotel, Garden 1994-2001
      - Photographs and Negatives 1993 (Box 21)
      - Architectural Analysis and Preservation Plan 1994 (Box 21)
      - Project File 1999-2000 (Box 21)
      - Project Files 1994-2001, 18 folders (Box 22)
    - Fayette State Park, Architectural Drawings, blue line prints (Tube 70)
    - Feldkamp Residence 2001, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Flat Rock
      - Smith Hotel and Wagar House
        - Wagar House Front Porch Restoration Specifications 2001 (Box 22)
        - Phase 2: Re-bid 2004 (Box 22)
        - Phase 3 Specifications 2005 (Box 22)
        - Rehabilitation Master Plan 2002, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - Photographs 2001, 8 volumes (Box 22)
        - Historic Preservation Master Plan 2002, 4 folders (Box 23)
        - Project Files 2001-2004, 26 folders (Box 23)
        - Smith School Architectural Drawing, pencil and ink original drawings (Tube 71)
      - Reading School
        - Rehabilitation Master Plan 2002 (Box 23)
        - Project Files 2001-2004, 8 folders (Box 24)
        - Architectural Drawings, pencil and ink original drawings, and copies of original plan (Tube 72)
    - Fort Michilimackinac, Mackinaw City, Architectural Drawings, copies of blueprints (Tube 73)
    - Fort Wayne Park, Detroit
      - Physical Historical Building Survey undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Building Inventory Notebook #1 undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Building Inventory Notebook #2 2002, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - Final Master Plan 2003, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - Compact Disks with images undated, 8 optical disks CDs (Box 24)
      - Inventory Negatives undated (Box 24)
      - Project Files 2002-2003, 5 folders (Box 24)
      - Project Files 2002-2003, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Fox Theater Building, Detroit
      - Certification Application 1988 (Box 25)
      - Project File 1987-1988 (Box 25)
    - Frank Residence, Messer Road, Chelsea, Architectural Drawings, original principle and ink on mylar drawings, blue line prints (Tube 74)
    - Charles Lange Freer House, Detroit
      - Project Notebook 1987-1993 (Box 25)
      - Historic Preservation Report 1994 (Box 25)